This is the New START treaty or to give
it its official title, the treaty
between the United States of America and
the Russian Federation on measures for
the further reduction and limitation of
strategic offensive arms. At time of
recording, it is the last remaining
treaty limiting the number of nuclear
weapons in the world. Signed in April
2010 by Barack Obama and then Russian
President Dmitri Medvidev, it places a
hard cap on the number of nukes that
both Russia and America can have
deployed at any one time. The cap of
1,550
nuclear warheads might sound like quite
a lot, but it represented the fewest
nuclear weapons those countries had ever
had ready to fire at one another at any
one time. In February 2026, which by the
time you're watching this might be now
that changes because on the 4th of that
month, this treaty runs out.
We're about to live in the in a world
where strategic nuclear weapons of the
two greatest nuclear powers are
uncapped.
>> This is Elelliana Johns. Elelliana is a
senior research associate for the
Nuclear Information Project at the
Federation of American Scientists.
>> The history of our organization is
actually pretty interesting. So, we were
founded in 1945 by some of the uh
scientists who participated in the
Manhattan Project. So from that legacy,
uh, my team works on kind of the way we
like to frame it is we we like to we're
trying to pull back the curtain on
nuclear secrecy because nuclear weapons
really are able to thrive in secrecy
when they're not talked about, when
they're when they're when they're uh
hidden from the public view, from public
scrutiny.
>> Elelliana has written extensively on the
past, present, and future of nuclear
weapons. And so she seemed like the
perfect person to fill me in on what the
ending of this crucial treaty actually
means.
>> It will be the first time in more than
50 years that the United States and
Russia or I guess the former Soviet
Union are not bound by some form of
strategic arms control arrangement or
engaged in um dialogue about um their
nuclear weapons. What that means is
after the treaty expires, the US and
Russia won't be bound or obligated by
any agreement. So they'll have the
capacity to upload hundreds and hundreds
of nuclear warheads
if they don't decide to continue abiding
by these treaty limits um or if they
don't reach some other form of
agreement.
>> There couldn't be a worse time for this
to be happening. One of the reasons that
this treaty is expiring in the first
place is that geopolitical tensions are
currently desperately high. And I wrote
that line before the US kidnaps Majuro
and whatever the other major military
world event is which happens between us
filming this, editing it and getting